I now wanted to talk about Yemen again,
one of the most overlooked
countries in the world, one of the most
important countries in the Middle East
vis-a-vis national security.
And I also believe this is one of the
most underreported stories of the week.
So, let's move on to Yemen, which could
be
the match
that ignites at least a regional war
across the Middle East. Yemen's
Iran-aligned Houthis announced on Monday
that they were imposing a naval blockade
against Saudi Arabia.
A move that could launch the price of
gas way past where it is right now.
Let's take a look at this clip from Good
Morning America.
>> This morning, new fears the war with
Iran could be expanding with the
Iran-backed Houthis from Yemen now
threatening to block Saudi oil from
transiting another key waterway. This
one connecting the Red Sea to the Indian
Ocean. With traffic in the Strait of
Hormuz already slowing to a crawl,
cutting off the Red Sea could cause oil
prices to spike even further and gas
prices now more than $4 a gallon as
well.
>> I'm proud to say I called this a week
ago.
Uh
Listen, one of the goals with this show
is to predict the news before anybody
else reports it. That was a a big
example. I'm I'm one of the few people
inside or outside government that really
follows Yemen closely.
Um check this out. I think this is just
nuts. This is what the Houthis are
actually broadcasting
to Saudi ships on open channels. Listen
to this.
>> So far, it's calling you on channel 16.
According to the decision of Yemeni
armed forces in the date of July 202026,
we want all ships belonging to Saudi
enemy to proceed via the Red Sea and
Gulf of Aden. In case of non-compliance
of Yemeni armed forces decision, those
ships will be in our target. Over.
>> This requires a little bit of
explanation. Let's go back to 1990,
August the 2nd.
Iraqi troops invade and occupy Kuwait.
The Kuwaiti ruling family flees to uh
Taif, Saudi Arabia.
It just so happened that Yemen and Cuba
were non-permanent members of the United
Nations Security Council that year. And
so Secretary of State James Baker went
to the Yemenis and the Cubans, more the
Yemenis, and said, "Listen, we are at a
historic crossroads. You have to do the
right thing, and you have to vote yes on
the United Nations Security Council's um
uh
resolution to use force to kick the
Iraqis out of Kuwait. The whole world is
on our side. You need to be on the right
side, too."
And the Yemenis voted no.
The Yemenis decided to throw their lot
in with Saddam Hussein. There were 2
million Yemeni workers in Saudi Arabia
at that time. Every last one of them was
expelled from Saudi Arabia, and the
world has never been the same.
I flew into Yemen
on my very first trip to the country
in June of 1991.
I flew to Sana, the capital, from
Jeddah, along the Red Sea coast of Saudi
Arabia. For 20 minutes before the plane
landed, you could see
people living in cardboard boxes
or in makeshift lean-tos, no roofs,
tents.
2 million people thrown out of Saudi
Arabia on the same day. These are people
that can't afford shoes, that can't
afford food for their children and
water. To make matters worse,
as recently as the late 1970s, Yemen was
a net food exporter. And they decided to
stop growing food so they could replace
all the food with something called qat.
Q A T. Qat is like coca, but not as
potent. They chew it all day long, and
it's a stimulant. It's like drinking a
pot of coffee.
Well, now you see people sitting in
these little They look like tree houses
with old rifles guarding their qat.
Their children don't have food, but
there's plenty of qat to chew. Well,
then all these 2 million workers were
expelled from Saudi Arabia, there's no
food, there's no water, there are no
jobs, there's no housing.
I've been to Yemen five times over the
years, and every single time I go, it's
worse than the previous time.
For decades, the country was led by a
president named Ali Abdullah Saleh.
Saleh was close to Saudi Arabia. He was
also close to the United States,
but then he split with us
on this Saddam Hussein vote.
Immediately, a Yemeni civil war started.
And it wasn't just, you know, the good
guys versus the bad guys. It was a
multipart civil war, and you have
Al-Qaeda
fighting as part of that civil war.
Osama bin Laden's family originated in
Yemen in the eastern part of Yemen in an
area called the Hadramaut. Hadramaut
comes from two Arabic words, Hadar,
which means visitation vegetation, maut
means dead.
It says it's called dead vegetation
because it's so dry, literally nothing
can live there. Animals don't even live
there.
Well, that's where Al-Qaeda was based in
Yemen in this no man's land that nobody
else could go to.
They began attacking the central
government. In South Yemen, the former
communists began attacking the central
government. And the Shia Muslims in
northwestern
Yemen began attacking the the central
government. Ali Abdullah Saleh fled to
Saudi Arabia and took refuge there. The
Saudis reluctantly gave it to him. But
somebody was able to sneak into the
palace uh that he was living in and they
planted a bomb and it quite literally
blew his head off.
So, Ali Abdullah Saleh
no longer exists.
The last time I went to Yemen was in
2011 and I had gone there from Djibouti,
which as I mentioned in the last episode
is just about 9 mi across the water.
Something called the Bab-el-Mandeb where
the Horn of Africa almost meets the uh
the southwestern tip of the Arabian
Peninsula, right there.
And when I got into a cab in Sanaa, I
said to the to the driver, "So, how are
things going?" And he said, "Oh, things
are rough right now." He said the the uh
the Houthis are attacking the capital
city. And I said, "Yeah, I've read about
that. It's terrible." And he said,
"They're using drones against us." And I
said,
"The Houthis don't have drones."
And then I thought to myself,
"But we do."
In 2011, we were already involved in a
war
in Yemen in 2011 and nobody knew about
it. Thank you, Barack Obama.
Another American secret war.
So, now here we are all these years
later. The Houthis have overthrown
the um
the Yemeni government. They have taken
control of the Yemeni government even if
they don't control the whole of Yemen.
Uh they control the most important parts
of Yemen. So, what are they threatening
here specifically?
They are specifically threatening to
blow up
ships coming in and out
of Saudi Arabia, which really is Jeddah.
Most of those ships are oil tankers.
But, a good number of them are cargo
ships that are that are have come
through the Suez Canal and are going to
transit the Bab al-Mandab.
If the Yemenis do this,
it's going to force ships to go instead
of going through the Suez Canal and the
Bab al-Mandab to go all the way around
Africa,
which adds 30 days to the trip
and billions of gallons of fuel.
So,
we're talking about the entire planet
going into a recession
and having to fight what's going to be
out of control inflation
because this little group of bandits
has closed the Bab al-Mandab.
This is going to be a very serious
thing. So, how did the Saudis respond?
Well, they essentially can't. I mean,
there's a Saudi navy for what that's
worth, but the Saudi military has been
fighting the Houthis for more than a
decade and they lost.
The Houthis won.
Another thing that I learned when I was
living in Saudi Arabia
is that
even though the Saudis, you know,
economically, geographically, physically
dominate
the Yemenis, and especially the Houthis,
the Houthis are fierce fighters, and
they're not afraid of it anybody, but
the Saudis are afraid of them.
And so, this is going to be a serious
problem for the Saudis.
Let's talk for a second, though, about
the Israeli factor.
You might remember
6, 8, 10 months ago, whatever it
whatever it is, the Israeli government
recognized an area of Somalia called
Somaliland as an independent country.
It's not an independent country, even
though many of us, including me, wish
that it was. It's not an independent
country.
The Israelis are the only country in the
world that recognized Somaliland as
independent.
That's great for Somaliland. There's an
Israeli embassy now in Somaliland. So,
what do the Israelis get out of it?
They get an air base.
They get an air base that's about 100
miles from the Houthis.
And so, if Israeli shipping
is threatened in the Bab al-Mandab,
they are going to unleash F-35s and
attempt to blow the Houthis back to the
Stone Age. That's been tried in the
past, it doesn't work.
I think what we're going to end up
seeing here
is crimes against humanity.
We're going to see the port of Hodeidah
bombed repeatedly. And the last time the
Israelis did this, they bombed schools,
they bombed hospitals, and the Saudis,
they're just as guilty. Schools,
hospitals, children, private homes, it
makes no difference, they just bombed
everything.
I think we're going to see more of that.
I want to add one other thing, two other
things. Number one,
if the Saudis are attacked,
the Bahrainis are going to jump in,
because the Bahrainis and the Saudis are
joined at the hip. And if the Bahrainis
jump in, the Emirates probably will jump
in. Now, the Emirates appear to have
negotiated their own private one-to-one
deal with Iran. "We'll give you $3
billion in cash if you stop bombing us."
And the Iranians stopped.
But the Saudis and the Emirates, even
though they were on different sides of
the of the fight in Yemen,
um
if the Saudis were in danger, I think
the Emirates would jump in on the side
of the Saudis.
And then we have a full-fledged regional
war.
You have Saudi Arabia,
Kuwait, Bahrain,
the United Arab Emirates, Oman, Jordan,
and Israel
against Iran
and Yemen.
Qatar's going to try to remain neutral.
Oman's going to try to remain neutral,
but this is going to be a full-fledged
regional war. I want to add one other
thing.
Um back in 2010, I was working
I was working on the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee, and a local think
tank asked me if I would um participate
in a debate on Yemen.
I said, "Sure, why not?"
And so, you know, I I generally never
prepare for these things. I figure if if
I don't know these issues by now, I'm
never going to know them. I'm supposed
to be an expert. So, I just have to rely
on my own knowledge and my own
background.
I go to this event on Capitol Hill
having no idea that my debate is against
Senator Susan Collins.
So, she's there with a whole army of
aids, and she's got her notes, and she's
reading her note cards, and I'm just
sitting there on the stage, you know,
like looking at my watch and looking at
the crowd and waving at people.
And it comes time to to debate.
And I essentially said in the debate
what I just told you.
That the Yemenis are consistently
underestimated.
That they are scrappy and tough and mean
and fierce fighters and they are not
afraid of anybody. And even though Saudi
Arabia is bigger and richer and more
powerful, that the Yemenis were going to
win.
And I said,
"The US long said that it had no
national interests in Yemen. Indeed, it
has national interests. It's
counterterrorism,
counterpiracy,
and open trade through the
Bab-el-Mandeb."
Well, Senator uh
Collins disagreed with me. Okay, that's
fine. At the end I got up, I shook her
hand, and I went home.
The next day John Kerry, who was my
boss, walks into my office and says,
"Did you debate Senator Collins last
night?" And I said, "I did. And if I may
say so, I kicked her ass."
He didn't think that was funny.
And he just said to me, "Don't ever do
that again."
And then he walked out.